Walter Landauer Collection 1993.0057
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Walter Landauer Collection
1919-1996
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1993.0057
4.4 Linear Feet
Walter Landauer was born in Mannheim, Germany, on 15 July 1896 the son of S. Friedrich and Charlotte Ziegler Landauer. He attended the University of Frankfurt and received his doctorate from the University of Heidelberg in 1922. He held the position of Zoology Instructor from 1922-1924 at Heidelberg before accepting a position at the University of Connecticut in 1924 at the Experiment Station. From 1928 until his retirement in 1964, Landauer was a professor in the department of animal genetics. Landauer is known for his work in animal genetics, specifically chickens.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
Materials in the collection have been donated by Walter Landauer, Mrs. Elly Landauer and Dr. Hugh Clark. The files of correspondence between Emil Richter (and his staff) and Landauer regarding the acquisition of Kathe Kollwitz's artwork were transferred from the William Benton Museum of Art in September 2006.
Arrangement
Series I: 1935 Crackdown at UConn (1934-1935)
Series II: Biographical and Personal Papers (1924-1996)
Series III: Research and Publications (1919-1980)
Series IV: Gustav Landauer (1899-1994)
Biography
Walter Landauer was born in Mannheim, Germany, on 15 July 1896 the son of S. Friedrich and Charlotte Ziegler Landauer. He attended the University of Frankfurt and received his doctorate from the University of Heidelberg in 1922. Landauer emigrated to the United States in 1924 and was naturalized in 1940. He held the position of Zoology Instructor from 1922-1924 at Heidelberg before accepting a position at the University of Connecticut in 1924 at the Experiment Station. From 1928 until his retirement in 1964, Landauer was a professor in the department of animal genetics. Landauer is known for his work in animal genetics, specifically chickens. After his retirement, he relocated to London where he became honorary research associate in the department of Zoology and Comparative Anatomy at the University College in London. Landauer was married several times; Naomi E. Beck (1939), Elly Trude Kiewe (1964). He died in February 1978.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, notes and publications of >Dr. Landauer demonstrating his interests in genetics and related issues. Correspondents include noted colleagues, University administrators and Richard Stroud (Birdman of Alcatraz). Also included is a collection of the published works of Landauer's uncle, Gustav Landauer. The "1935 Crackdown" concerns a ban on public discussion of military training on campus which was interpreted as anti-war agitation at the college. The original Dunn-Landauer correspondence listed in Series II is located at the American Philosophical Society.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
American Philosophical Society Proceedings. (v. 109, #4) Dodd Periodicals
Auerbach, Charlotte. The Science of Genetics.
Waddington, C.H. The Strategy of the Genes.
Pearson, Karl. The Life, Letter and Labors of Frances Galton.
Baker, John R. Abraham Trembley of Geneva.
Lind, L.R. Aldrovandi on Chickens.
Hoaldy, Charles J. Trauscuption.
Thompson, C.J.S. The Mystery and Lore of Monsters.
Krizenecky, Jaroslav.. Fundamenta Genetica.
Kukenthal, Dr. Willy. Handbuch der Zoologie.
Waddington, C.H. Principles of Embryology.
Neel, James V. Changing Perspectives on the Genetic Effects of Radiation.
Stern, Curt. Sherwood, Eva R. The Origin of Genetics.
Haldane, J.B.S. Heredity and Politics.
Ludmerer, Kenneth M. Genetics and American Society.
Ford, E.B. Genetic Polymorphism.
Ford, Clellan S. Beach, Frank A. Patterns of Sexual Behavior.
Huxley, T.H.; Huxley, Julian. Evolution and Ethics.
Murphy, Douglas P. Congenital Malformations.
Lenz, Widukind. Medical Genetics.
Haldane, J.B.S. The Biochemistry of Genetics.
Waddington, C.H. Organisers and Genes.
Kreybig, Thomas Von. Die Ontogeneese Wird Zum Schicksal.
Sturn, Curt. Genetic Mosaics and Other Essays.
Jackson, C.M. The effects of Inanition and Malnutrition opon Growth and Structure.
Chauvois, Louis. William Harvey.
Beadle, George W. Genetics and Modern Biology.
Goldschmidt, Richard B. Physiological Genetics.
Olby, Robert C. Origins of Mendelism.
Levine, Rachmiel.; Soskin, Samuel. Carbohydrate Metabolism.
Euler, U.S. Von. Tobacco Alkaloids and Related Compounds.
Stockard, Charles R. The Genetics of Endocrinic Basis for Differences in Form and Behavior.
Needham, Joseph. The Chemistry of Life.
Bertalanffy, Ludwig Von. Modern Theories of Development.
Russell, E.S. Form and Function.
Bertalauffy, Ludwig Von. Problems of Life.
Mayr, Otto. The Origins of Feedback Control.
Waddington, C.H. New Patterns in Genetics and Development.
Huxley, Julian. Problems in Relative Growth.
Weiss, Paul. Principles of Development.
Krahl, M.E. The Action of Insulin on Cells.
Wagner, Robert P.; Mitchell, Herschel K. Genetics and Metabolism.
Bernard, Claude. An Introduction to the Study of Experimental Medicine
Jevons, F.R. The Biochemical Approach to Life.
Renan, Ernest. The Future of Science.
Radot, Rene Vallery. The Life of Pasteur.
Schmalhausen, I.I. Factors of Evolution.
Schull, W.J.; Neel, J.V. The Effect of Exposure to the Atomic Bombs on Pregnancy Termination in Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
Ryan, Francis J.; Sager, Ruth. Cell Heredity.
Burnham, Geo. P. The History of The Hen Fever.
Pearson, Karl. The Grammar of Science.
Rendel, J.M. Canalisation and Gene Control.
Wheeler, William Morton. Foibles of Insects and Men.
Fabre, J.H. The Life of the Spider.
Fabre, J.H. The Life and Love of the Insect.
Goldschmidt, Richard B. Theoretical Genetics.
Lerner, Michael I. Genetic Homeostasis.
Child, C.M. Patterns and Problems of Development.
Bertalauffy, Ludwig Von. An Introduction to Theoretical Biology.
Stockard, Charles R. Theories in Form and Behavior.
Gruneberg, Hans. The Pathology of Development.
Dunn, L.C. Sinnott, Edmund W. Dobzhansky, Theodosius. Principles of Genetics.
Becker, Peter Emil.; Lenz, Widukind.; Vogel, Friedrich.; Wendt, G. Gerhard. Humangenetik.
Roux, Wilhelm. Entwickelungsmechanik Der Organismen.
Lacroix, Adrien.; Ragot, Charles L. A Graphic Table Combining Logarithms and Anti-Logarithms.
Baltzer, Fritz. Theodor Boveri.
Bethe, Albrecht. Allgemeine Physiologie
Wheeler, William Morton. Ants: Their Structure, Development and Behavior.
Hadorn, Ernst. Letalfaktoren.
Bernard, Claude. Phenomenes de la Vie.
Shenwood, Eva. Origin of Genetics.
Berrill, N.J. Growth, Development, and Pattern.
Williams, Roger J. Biochemical Individuality.
Ganpp, K. Korperbau and Kharadei.
Hoadly, Charles J. Records of the Colony and Plantation of New Haven.
Taylor, Norman B.; Best, Charles H. The Physiological Basis of Medical Practice.
Mintz, Beatrice. Environmental Influences on Prenatal Development.
Clark, A.J. Hanbuch Der Experimentellen Pharmakologie.
Iltis, Hugo. Gregor Johann Mendel.
Gray, Peter. Encyclopedia of Biological Sciences.
Simpson, George Gaylord.; Roe, Anne. Quantitative Zoology.
Wigglesworth, V.B. Control of Growth and Form.
National Association of Sciences. Biological Effects of Atomic Radiation.
Ariens, E.J. Molecular Pharmacology.
Fulton, John F. Howell's Textbook of Physiology.
Thompson, Sir A. Landsborough. A New Dictionary of Birds.
Mach, Ernst. Erkenntnis und Irrtum.
Baltzer, Fritz. Theodor Boveri.
Sturtevant, A.H. A History of Genetics.
Cannon, Walter Bradford. The Way of an Investigator.
Kretschmer, Ernst. Korperbau und Charakter.
Weisham, A. Vortrago... Theorie.
Schoenheimer, Rudolf. The Dynamic State of Body Constituents.
Kuize, Haus Shiblee. ...der Genetics.
Waddington, C.H.; Reeve, E.C.R. Quantitative Inheritance.
Ludwig, W. Rechts-Links-Problem.
National Academic Sciences. Scientific Aspects of Pest Control.
Curie, Eve. Madame Curie.
Jousen, Haus F. Function.
Rensch, Dr. Bernhard. Neuere Probleme Der Abstammungslehre.
Loeb, Jacques. The Organism as a Whole.
Duhamel, Bernard. Morphogenese Pathologique.
Liebig, J. Von. Die...der Ideau.
Stubbe, Hans. Kurze Geschichte der Genetik.
Weismann, August. Deszendenztheorie.
Lichtenbergs Briefe, hrsg. von Albert Leitzmann und Carl Schüddekopf C9782
Schillers briefwechsel mit Körner A8635
Education, Higher; Photographs; Geneticists; Correspondence; Publications (documents); United States (nation); Academic freedom; Chickens; Freedom of speech; Genetics; University of connecticut. Department of Animal Genetics; University of Connecticut; Landauer, Gustav, 1870-1919
- Series I: 1935 Crackdown at UConn, 1934-1935
  - Gumbel Affair—University of Heidelberg (Box 1)
  - Social Problems Club (Box 1)
    - Wechsler, James (Box 1)
    - Student Senate Statement, 1935 (Box 1)
  - McCracken, Charles C., 1935 (Box 1)
  - "The background of the events..." (Box 1)
  - "Opinions concerning the ruling..." (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings (Box 1)
  - "Academic Freedom, compulsory military training, the Social Problems Club, and the Board of Trustees", 1934-1935 (Box 1)
- Series II: Biographical and Personal Papers, 1924-1996
  - Academic History, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical information, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1989 (Box 1)
    - Dunn-Landauer (transcriptions), 1927-1970 (Box 1)
    - Haskins, Caryl P., 1952 (Box 1)
    - Landauer, E. - Clark, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - Richter, Emil (Kathe Kollwitz artwork] (6 ff), 1930-1972 (Box 1)
    - University of Connecticut, 1961-1978 (Box 1)
    - Waugh, Albert E., 1965 (Box 1)
  - National Medal of Science, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
- Series III: Research and Publications, 1919-1980
  - Biological Publications ( 6 bound vols.), 1922-1961 (Box 1)
  - Creeper research articles, 1925-1951 (Box 2)
  - Creeper research articles, 1957-1969 (Box 2)
  - Research notes (10 ff), undated (Box 2)
  - McCarthy era clippings, 1951-1954 (Box 2)
  - Pesticides articles, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
  - Published Articles (in German), 1919-1923 (Box 2)
  - Published Articles (in German), 1923-1929 (Box 3)
  - Reprints (Landauer, 3 ff), 1926-1977 (Box 3)
  - Reprints—"Hatchability of Chicken eggs...", 1951-1973 (Box 3)
  - Der Sozialist (3 vols.), 1909-1914 (Box 3)
  - Stroud's Digest of the Diseases of Birds, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Stroud Case
    - Articles and publications, 1962-1975 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1944-1971 (Box 3)
    - Summaries, 1919-1944 (Box 3)
  - Symposium—Society for Developmental Biology, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Thalidomide
    - Articles, undated, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Thesis, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Watergate, 1974 (Box 3)
- Series IV: Gustav Landauer, 1899-1994
  - Varia by and about, 1899-1924 (Box 4)
  - Verhandlungen des Provisoischen Nationalrats, Volksstaat Bayern, 1918-1919 (Box 4)
  - Aufruf zum Sozialismus, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Skepsis und Mystik, 1923 (Box 4)
  - Levine, Eugen, 1994 (Box 4)